{"tossups": [{"question": "Eleanor Billington and Susanna White were two of the four women charged with preparing for this event. James Baker claimed that this event occurred around Michaelmas. A governor ordered four of his men to go on a \u201cfowling\u201d mission three days before this event, which celebrated the provision of supplies by Massasoit. William Bradford organized this event after a successful corn harvest in 1621. For ten points, name this event in which the Plymouth Pilgrims held a feast of gratitude.", "answer": "the First Plymouth<b> Thanksgiving</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> first Thanksgiving</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country is of primary interest to the activist group Brothers to the Rescue, which had planes shot down in 1996. Edward Lansdale directed Operation Mongoose against this country, which was also the focus of the Helms-Burton Act. It sent numerous mental patients to the U.S. during the Mariel boatlift. The CIA trained Brigade 2506, which tried to invade this country in April 1961. For ten points, name this Caribbean island country, the site of the failed, U.S.-backed Bay of Pigs invasion.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Cuba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In December 2016, this leader announced his country\u2019s official unit of currency would become the Toman. This leader was elected in 2013 with the slogan of a \u201cGovernment of prudence and hope\u201d after Mahmoud Ahmadinejad served for two terms. This leader negotiated with the P5+1 countries regarding his country\u2019s nuclear program, with a Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action agreed on in 2015. For ten points, name this current President of Iran.", "answer": "Hassan<b> Rouhani</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. \u201cSlick\u201d Goodlin demanded $150,000 to perform this action, so the honor went to the second choice instead; that man fell off his horse and injured his ribs, so Jack Ridley fashioned a broom handle into a lever to help seal the hatch. This event, which took place above Rogers Dry Lake in the Mojave Desert, utilized the Bell XS-1, a rocket-powered airplane. For ten points, name this October 14, 1947 accomplishment performed by Chuck Yeager.", "answer": "first<b> breaking</b> of<b> the sound barrier</b> via airplane (accept descriptions of first<b> breaking Mach 1</b> in an airplane; accept additional correct information if given; prompt on correct-but-not-sought answers, like \u201cChuck Yeager\u2019s flight\u201d) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A media building owned by this leader was rammed by a wheel-loader at the start of the Bulldozer Revolution. A Chinese embassy was accidentally bombed during a NATO intervention against this leader called Operation Allied Force. This man was accused of failing to prevent Ratko Mladic [m\u2019lah-ditch] from perpetrating the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-neetz-ah] massacre by the prosecutors of his war crime trial, though he died of a heart attack in 2006 before a verdict could be reached. For ten points, name this Serbian president of Yugoslavia during the Kosovo War.", "answer": "Slobodan<b> Milosevi\u00b4c</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The arrest of an advocate of this cause inspired another advocate to sneak a knife into the National Gallery and slash the<em> Rokeby Venus</em>. A proponent of this cause was trampled to death in the Epsom Derby in 1913. The Cat and Mouse Act applied to people who were imprisoned for supporting this cause, whose advocates included Millicent Fawcett and several members of the Pankhurst family. For ten points, name this cause achieved in Great Britain in 1918, which effectively doubled the size of the country\u2019s electorate.", "answer": "women\u2019s<b> suffrage</b> in the United Kingdom", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Along with two friends, the main character of this novel risks punishment by swimming naked across a canal in the middle of the night to rendezvous with three French women. This book\u2019s protagonist feels remorse over a stabbing a man whom he discovers through his papers was a printer named Gerard Duval. In this novel, Kemmerich\u2019s boots are acquired by the main character after the death of Fredrich Muller, and Kat\u2019s death causes Paul Baumer to lose interest in fighting in World War I. For ten points, name this novel by Erich Maria Remarque.", "answer": "<b> All Quiet on the Western Front</b> (or<b> Im Westen nichts Neues</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "During these conflicts, the Thirteen Factories were twice destroyed. James Bremer used gunboats to great effect in this conflict and blockaded the Pearl River. The second of these conflicts began when the <em>Arrow</em> was seized. Lin Zexu sent a letter asking \u201cwhere is your conscience?\u201d to Queen Victoria in the first of these conflicts, which ended with the cessation of Hong Kong Island in the unequal Treaty of Nanking. For ten points, name this series of conflicts between Great Britain and China sparked by drug exports.", "answer": "(First and/or Second)<b> Opium</b> War(s) (prompt on descriptions of wars between Great Britain and China before mentioned) Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The surrender of a fort in this state was demanded \u201cIn the name of the Great Jehovah and the Continental Congress!\u201d A city in this state names a \u201cconspiracy\u201d defused by George Washington. A Revolutionary War battle in this state consisted of engagements at Freeman\u2019s Farm and Bemis Heights and led to the surrender of John Burgoyne. For ten points, name this home state of Newburgh, Fort Ticonderoga, and Saratoga, as well as engagements on Manhattan Island.", "answer": "<b> New York</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Laurens Janzoon Coster is alleged to have invented one method for producing these objects. Aldus Manutius and William Caxton were among the earliest producers of one type of these objects, examples of which produced before 1501 are called incunabula. These objects are typically in codex form, and the production of these objects was revolutionized in Mainz by improvements on metal moveable type. Manuscripts were quickly replaced by, for ten points, what bound objects, first mass produced by Johannes Gutenberg?", "answer": "printed<b> books</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Edward Nkoloso trained people in this occupation by rolling them down hills in oil drums in Zambia. Yang Liwei\u2019s work in this occupation as part of the Shenzhou project culminated in 2003. Ilan Ramon became the first Israeli citizen to carry out this job. In 1962, the citizens of Perth, Australia turned on their lights to honor an American in this occupation passing overhead. For ten points, name this occupation held by the Mercury Seven, including John Glenn.", "answer": "<b> astronaut</b>s (accept<b> Afronaut</b>s; accept<b> hang tian yuan</b> or<b> yu hang yuan</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, two rival partiess were nicknamed the Sharks and the Tailless. A revolt among tobacco planters in this country led to the assassination of its president, Ulises Heureaux [you-lee-zays ay-oh-rokes], in 1899. The Military Intelligence Service, or SIM, was a secret police force operated in this country by Johnny Abbes. Another leader of this country had three sisters of the Mirabal family assassinated in 1960 and notoriously executed people who pronounced the word \u201cparsley\u201d a certain way. For ten points, name this country once ruled by Rafael Trujillo that borders Haiti.", "answer": "<b> Dominican Republic</b> (or<b> Rep\u00b4ublica Dominicana</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The Royal Navy ship<em> HMS Amethyst</em> was trapped on this river for several months in 1949. A 1954 flood here devastated Hubei Province, and a series of canyons along its banks are the site of a project that displaced 1.3 million people and started producing power in 2003. This river is referred to in its native country as Chang Jiang. The Three Gorges Dam was built on, for ten points, what Chinese river that empties into the sea at Shanghai?", "answer": "<b> Yangtze</b> River (or<b> Chang Jiang</b> before mention)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An inaugural address delivered by this U.S. president relates the story of soldier Martin Treptow, who died in World War I. Yellow ribbons were worn to celebrate the inauguration of this president. A speech delivered by this president to the National Association of Evangelicals claimed that the Judeo-Christian tradition was superior to the collective mentality of the Soviet Union, which he dubbed an \u201cEvil Empire.\u201dFor ten points, name this president whose first inauguration coincided with the end of the Iran Hostage Crisis in 1980.", "answer": "Ronald<b> Reagan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A stonemason named Elias of Dereham may have provided a building he designed with a copy of this document, which is to be read at cathedrals twice a year. This document exempted the seacoast from a stipulation calling for the removal of royal fish weirs. Shortly after this document\u2019s adoption, a conflict that included a siege of Dover broke out. The First Barons\u2019 War arose after the creation of, for ten points, what document that was sealed at Runnymede by King John in 1215?", "answer": "<b> Magna Carta</b> Libertatum (accept the<b> Great Charter</b> of the Liberties; accept<b> Magna Charta</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 2002, Isioma Daniel became the subject of one of these works after joking about the Miss World beauty pageant. Creators of these declarations are known as (+)</b><em><b> muftis</b></em><b>, though there is no international body to decide</b><em><b> fiqh</b></em> <b>[feek] controversies over these declarations. (*) </b>Osama bin Laden issued two of these statements prior to becoming head of al-Qaeda. For ten points, give this term for a legal opinion delivered by an Islamic jurist, one of which was delivered by Ayatollah Khomeini in 1989 authorizing the murder of Salman Rushdie for publishing<em> The Satanic Verses</em>.", "answer": "<b> fatwa</b>s (or<b> fatawa</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. Arthur Chapman served as the translator of this oration. This speech declares \u201cIt is the young men who say yes and no\u201d and describes how \u201clittle children are freezing to death\u201d and how some people \u201chave run away to the hills;\u201d its speaker comments \u201cMaybe I shall find them among the dead.\u201d This speech was given after a (+) loss at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain in 1877 forced its speaker to capitulate to Oliver Howard. This speech ends with a declaration made \u201cfrom (*)</b> where the sun now stands\u201d by a speaker whose \u201cheart is sick and sad.\u201d For ten points, name this speech given by a chief of the Nez Perce, noting the end of his war against the United States.", "answer": "<b> Chief Joseph\u2019s surrender</b> speech (or the \u201c<b>I Will Fight No More Forever</b>\u201d speech; accept descriptive answers relating to<b> Chief Joseph surrendering</b>; accept<b> Nez Perce surrender </b>speech before \u201cNez Perce\u201d is read; prompt on partial answers) (3) <b>This man declared that \u201cwe should not emulate [Germany] only in armaments\u201d in</b> <b>support of the National Insurance Act. This man advocated for war to protect national honor in his Mansion House Speech, given in response to the (+) Agadir Crisis. He heavily increased a land tax to fund welfare programs in his \u201cPeople\u2019s Budget,\u201d and this leader\u2019s foreign minister advocated for the \u201cestablishment...of a national home of the (*) </b> Jewish people\u201d in the Balfour Declaration. For ten points, name this Welsh prime minister who led Britain through World War I. ANSWER: David<b> Lloyd George</b> (prompt on George)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man was blocked from command by Publius Sulpicius Rufus and was opposed in Hispania by Quintus Sertorius. He defeated his rival, Archelaus, at both Chaeronea and</b> <b>Orchomenus during the First (+)</b> <b>Mithridatic War. This ruler, who was awarded a grass</b> <b>crown for his bravery in the Social War and captured Jugurtha during a campaign in (*) </b>Numidia, began the practice of targeting political opponents with proscription. For ten points, name this Roman dictator who began the era of civil wars by defeating Gaius Marius.", "answer": "Lucius Cornelius<b> Sulla</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The wife of one participant in this event was enraged to see publicity photos showing the mistress Veronica Porch\u00b4e. Eddie Futch told Carlos Padilla to end this event, whose eventual winner claimed he lost five pounds of weight during it. The (+) \u201crope-a-dope\u201d strategy was ineffective early in this event, which took place in oppressively hot and humid conditions. The winner had angered the loser in pre-fight banter by calling him \u201cThe (*) </b> Gorilla\u201d. For ten points, name this third and final match between Muhammad Ali and Joe Frazier, fought in 1975 in the Philippines.", "answer": "<b> Thrilla in Manila</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> third</b> and/or<b> final</b> fight between<b> Ali and Frazier</b>, with names in either order, until \u201cMuhammad\u201d is read) (6) <b>At the first of these events, a participant was described as a \u201chatchet man\u201d after</b> <b>declaring that 1.6 million Americans had been killed in \u201cDemocrat wars.\u201d At a later one</b> <b>of these events, the opening statement \u201cWho am (+)</b> <b>I? Why am I here?\u201d was given by</b> <b>Admiral James Stockdale. A participant in another of these events said \u201cthat was really uncalled for, Senator\u201d after being told, (*)</b> \u201cyou\u2019re no Jack Kennedy.\u201d For ten points, name these televised events that have been contested between Bob Dole and Walter Mondale, Lloyd Bentsen and Dan Quayle, and more recently, Tim Kaine and Mike Pence. ANSWER:<b> Vice-Presidential debates</b> (accept descriptive answers; prompt on \u201cdebate;\u201d do not prompt on Presidential debate)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The</b><em><b> USS Panay</b></em><b> sank after evacuating survivors from this city. Prince Asuka was given immunity for events in this city, which was captured by the army of Matsui Iwane. A (+) safe zone in this city was created by John Rabe, a German businessman, saving thousands of lives. This capital of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom and the (*)</b> Republic of China was the site of a contest to kill 100 civilians with a sword and other such war crimes. For ten points, name this Chinese city that, in 1937, was subjected to a \u201crape\u201d by invading Japanese forces.", "answer": "<b> Nanking</b> (or<b> Nanjing</b>; accept descriptions of the Rape of<b> Nanking</b> or<b> Nanjing</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A photograph by (*) </b>Joe Rosenthal features this object being hoisted by six Marines. Jasper Johns showed only 48 stars on, for ten points, what national symbol that was raised after the Battle of Iwo Jima?", "answer": "<b> American flag</b> (accept any description of the<b> flag</b> of the<b> U</b>nited<b> S</b>tates of America; prompt on partial answers; prompt on \u201cwhite flag\u201d after \u201cwhite\u201d is read) Page 10", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Jehan Boinebroke was a merchant who dealt mainly in this good, which Pliny the Elder thought best came from Tarentum. Edward I had increased the duties on this</b> <b>good by a factor of (+)</b> <b>6 in order to help finance his French campaign. The seat of</b> <b>the speaker of the House of (*)</b> Lords is made of this good to represent its importance to the English economy. A village in Norfolk provides the name for the worsted type of this good, which could be felted if the fibers were soaked. For ten points, name this textile fiber obtained from sheep.", "answer": "<b> wool </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}